<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<steps>
	<step name="Identify anomalies and outliers in your data.">
		<text>Another important step of data cleansing is to identify unusual cases and remove them from the
		data set. In some situations, the outliers themselves might be the most interesting cases 
		(detecting fraudulent credit card transactions, for example), but in most cases outliers are simply the result of an incorrect measurement and should be removed from the data set. 
		This is exactly what we will
		do in this
		tutorial.</text>
	</step>

	<step name="Prepare the data.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Drag</activity>
				the
				<file>Titanic</file>
				data into the process.
			</task>
			<task>
				<acticity>Add</acticity>
				the operator
				<op>Select Attributes</op>
				and
				<activity>connect it</activity>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Change</activity>
				the
				<ui>Parameters</ui>
				so that you
				<activity>
					remove
					<value>Cabin</value>,
					<value>Life Boat</value>,
					<value>Name</value>, and
					<value>Ticket Number</value>
				</activity>.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			The result will be a data set only containing those columns we believe will contribute well to our
			outlier detection.
			We will use a distance-based outlier detection algorithm which calculates the
			<emph>Euclidean distance</emph>
			between the data points and marks those points which are farthest away from
			other data points as
			outliers. The Euclidean distance uses the distances between two data points for each individual attribute.
			Think about it: what is the effect on the distance if the attributes have different value ranges
			(one attribute between 0 and 5 and another attribute between 1 and 1000)? Attributes with
			larger values will contribute
			much more than those with smaller values. For this reason we should
			ensure that all attributes are
			using similar value
			ranges. This transformation is called
			<emph>Normalization</emph>.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Normalize the attribute value ranges.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Add</activity>
				the operator
				<op>Normalize</op>
				and
				<activity>connect it</activity>.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			In general, you should
			<emph>always</emph>
			normalize your data before you apply distance-based
			algorithms like outlier detection or k-Means
			clustering. Using the default parameters, the
			<op>Normalize</op>
			operator will perform a
			<emph>z-Transformation</emph>
			(also known as Standardization)
			which results in a mean value of 0 and a standard deviation of 1
			for each attribute. In other words, all of the attributes are on the same scale 
			after normalization and can be compared with one another.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Detect outliers.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Search</activity>
				for the operator <op>Detect Outlier (Distances)</op>,
				<activity>add it</activity>, and
				<activity>connect it</activity>
				to
				<op>Normalize</op>.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			This operator will identify the 10 examples which are farthest away from all others and mark
			them
			as outliers. It creates a new column named
			<value>outlier</value>
			with
			<value>true</value>
			as the value for the outliers and
			<value>false</value>
			for all other examples.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Remove outliers from example set.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Add</activity>
				<op>Filter Examples</op>
				to the process and
				<activity>connect</activity>
				it to the previous operator and also to
				the result port on the right.
			</task>
			<task>
				In its Parameters,
				<activity>add a new filter</activity>
				with
				<value>Outlier</value>,
				<value>equals</value>, and
				<value>false</value>
				as values.
			</task>
			<task>
				<icon>16/media_play.png</icon> <activity>Run</activity>
				the process.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			The process might run for some time but will switch to the Results view automatically when
			it is finished. You will notice that the result is a data set with 1299 examples - the 10
			outliers have successfully been removed.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Use breakpoints to see intermediate results.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Go back</activity>
				to the
				<ui>Design</ui>
				view.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Right-click</activity>
				on
				<op>Detect Outlier (Distances)</op>
				and
				<activity>select</activity>
				<value>Breakpoint after</value>
				in the menu.
				Note that a small icon appears at the bottom of the operator after you added the breakpoint.
			</task>
			<task>
				<icon>16/media_play.png</icon> <activity>Run</activity>
				the process again.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			The process is paused at the breakpoint and the intermediate results are shown. 
			This makes breakpoints a useful tool for debugging your process! All 1309 examples
			are still in the data set at this point of the process. <emph>Click the <icon>16/media_end.png</icon> <ui>Resume</ui> icon in the toolbar to continue</emph> 
			the process and see the final result.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Congratulations!">
		<text>Awesome, you found 10 outliers in your data and sucessfully removed them! This cleansing step can often improve the quality of your models. As usual, try the 
		challenges below and move on to the next tutorial:</text>
		
		<questions>
			<question>
				How would you change the process so it finds 20 outliers instead of 10?
			</question>
			<question>
				How can you change the process to only show outliers instead of removing them?
			</question>
			<question>
				 Replace the outlier detection operator with <op>Detect Outlier (LOF)</op> 
				 and add a <emph>breakpoint</emph> after this operator before you execute. 
				 What is the difference to before?
			</question>
			<question>
				How do you now need to change the filter to only keep the top outliers?
			</question>
		</questions>
	</step>
</steps>