<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<steps>
	<step name="Rotating from long to wide table formats.">
		<text>In this tutorial, you will learn about another common data blending technique, namely the
		<emph>Pivoting</emph>
		of data. You might be familiar with the concept of Pivoting from BI tools or Excel: 
		rotate the data from a long table format (one attribute with a lot of examples) into a wide table format (lots of attributes with a single example). 
		This transformation is especially useful after an aggregation since
		the
		aggregated information is always stored in a long format. Machine learning models, however,
		need
		the data to be stored in
		a wide column format so you will encounter this preprocessing step
		frequently
		before you start with the actual modeling.</text>
	</step>

	<step name="Prepare the data.">
		<info>
			Let’s start by creating a table that shows how many passengers were in each class, broken down by gender.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Drag</activity>
				the
				<file>Titanic</file>
				data into the process.
			</task>
			<task>
				<acticity>Add</acticity>
				the operator
				<op>Aggregate</op>
				and
				<activity>connect it</activity>.
			</task>
			<task>
				In its
				<ui>Parameters</ui>,
				<activity>select</activity>
				<value>Passenger Class</value>
				and
				<value>Sex</value>
				as
				<param>group by attributes</param>.
			</task>
			<task>
				Also use
				<value>Passenger Class</value>
				with function
				<value>count</value>
				as a new
				entry for
				<param>aggregation attributes</param>.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			The result will be a table with three columns:
			<value>Passenger Class</value>,
			<value>Sex</value>, and the count for each of
			those combinations. The first row is
			<value>First</value>,
			<value>Female</value>
			with a count of
			<value>144</value>, the second row is
			<value>First</value>,
			<value>Male</value>
			with a count of
			<value>179</value>
			and so on. All combinations of the passenger class and the gender
			are represented as rows which is
			why we call this a
			<emph>long</emph>
			table format.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Pivot the data.">
		<info>
			Let’s transform the long table format into a wide format that will make the number of males and females in each class a bit clearer.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Search</activity>
				for the operator
				<op>Pivot</op>,
				<activity>add it</activity>,
				and
				<activity>connect it</activity>
				to
				<op>Aggregate</op>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Select</activity>
				the operator to see its
				<ui>Parameters</ui>.
				<activity>Use</activity>
				<value>Sex</value>
				as the
				<param>group attribute</param>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Use</activity>
				<value>Passenger Class</value>
				as
				<param>index attribute</param>.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			The resulting data set has four columns and two rows. Each row represents one of the values from the <value>Sex</value> column 
			(the <param>group attributes</param> parameter). The three different
			values of the
			<param>index attribute</param>
			(
			<value>passenger class</value>
			) become the three new columns. The actual values in the table are representing the
			counts
			from the aggregation for the combination of the group (gender) with the index value (or
			subgroup), which is the passenger class in our case. For example, we will get 144 females who
			booked first
			class.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Renaming attributes with regular expressions.">
		<info>
			The names of the new columns reflect how they were created, but this is not always the easiest to read. You could use the
			operator
			<op>Rename</op>
			for manually renaming the three attributes to something nicer, like "Passenger
			Class First".
			<op>Rename</op>
			is the way to go if you only have few attributes which should be renamed,
			but we will take a more
			advanced approach which would allow you to
			rename hundreds of
			attributes at a time.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Search</activity>
				for the operator
				<op>Rename by Replacing</op>,
				<activity>add it</activity>, and
				<activity>connect it</activity>
				to
				<op>Pivot</op>.
			</task>
			<task>
				Also
				<activity>connect the operator</activity>
				to the result port on the right.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Copy</activity> <value>count\((.*)\)_(.*)</value>   
				into the <param>replace what</param> parameter field. 
				Make sure that you get all the parentheses right!
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Copy</activity>
				<value>$1 $2</value>
				into the
				<param>replace by</param> parameter.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			You might already be familiar with <emph>regular expressions</emph> (this is the name for the strange
			parameters we have used for the renaming). They are a powerful tool and can be
			found in many
			different places in RapidMiner. The expression you have used for <param>replace what</param>
			means that you look for something between <value>count(</value> and <value>)_</value> and then something else after the
			underscore. Those two elements are identified later by the round brackets.  Each time you use round brackets, you define 
			a new so-called <emph>capturing group</emph> which you can refer to in the definition of the replacement.
			Since the round brackets have a special meaning here, we need to quote the brackets in the name itself with a
			backslash. Finally, we can use the capturing groups in the <param>replace by</param>
			parameter with the dollar sign and the number identifying the group. <value>$1</value> is for
			the content of the first group, which always happens to be "Passenger Class", and <value>$2</value> is 
			for identifying the second group.  Those are the three different classes "First", "Second", and "Third".
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Run the process.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity><icon>16/media_play.png</icon> Run</activity> the process.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			Your data set should now have column names that look like <emph>Passenger Class First</emph>.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Congratulations!">
		<text>You rotated an aggregated data set from a long to a wide table format - good job! <op>Pivot</op> can be difficult to configure sometimes.  
		Just keep in mind that the <param>groups</param> parameter will end up in the rows with one row per group while the values of the <param>index attribute</param> 
		parameter will define the new columns.</text>

		<questions>
			<question>
				Add a breakpoint after "Aggregate". Run the process and check out the long table format. How many rows does it have? 
				Resume the process and compare the long format to wide format.  Don't forget to remove the breakpoint if you no longer need it.
			</question>
			<question>
				Can you change the process so that the column names will be changed to "First Passenger Class", 
				"Second Passenger Class", and "Third Passenger Class"?
			</question>
			<question>
				Can you also change them to just say "First Class", "Second Class", and "Third Class"?
			</question>
			<question>
				Change the Pivot so that the gender is transformed into new columns and the class is defining three groups of data.
				How many columns and rows are you getting now?
			</question>
			<question>
				Try to adapt the renaming so that it just uses the gender as column names after the new Pivoting.
			</question>
		</questions>
		
		<info>
			Don't worry if you had trouble with challenges 2, 3, or 5. Regular expressions can be difficult at first but 
			they are definitely worth learning. Maybe a book can help you or you will find a lot of training resources 
			<link url="http://www.ocpsoft.org/opensource/guide-to-regular-expressions-in-java-part-1/">online</link>
			.
		</info>
	</step>
</steps>
