<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<steps>
	<step name="Aggregate data and pivot.">
		<text>In this tutorial, you will learn about another common data blending technique, namely the
		<emph>Pivoting</emph>
			of data. You might be familiar with the concept of Pivoting from BI tools or Excel:
			rotate the data from a long table format (one attribute with a lot of examples) into a wide table format
			(lots of attributes with a single example). This transformation is especially useful to aggregate
			information along two or more dimensions as a step to prepare the data for machine learning. Machine
			learning models need the data to be stored in a wide table format so you will encounter this preprocessing
			step frequently before you start with the actual modeling.
		</text>
	</step>

	<step name="Pivot the data.">
		<info>
			Let’s create a table that shows how many passengers were in each class, broken down by gender.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Drag</activity>
				the
				<file>Titanic</file>
				data into the process.
			</task>
			<task>
				<acticity>Add</acticity>
				the operator
				<op>Pivot</op>
				and
				<activity>connect it</activity>.
			</task>
			<task>
				In its
				<ui>Parameters</ui>,
				<activity>add</activity>
				<value>Sex</value>
				to the
				<param>group by attributes</param>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Select</activity>
				<value>Passenger Class</value>
				as
				<param>column grouping attribute</param>.
			</task>
			<task>
				Also use
				<value>Passenger Class</value>
				with function
				<value>count</value>
				as a new
				entry for
				<param>aggregation attributes</param>.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			The resulting data table has four columns and two rows. Each row represents one of the values from the
			<value>Sex</value>
			column, (the <param>group by attributes</param> parameter).
			The three different values of the <param>column grouping attribute</param> (
			<value>Passenger Class</value>) become the three new columns. The actual values in the table are
			representing the counts of each combination of groups in the rows, i.e. the gender, and the groups in the
			columns, which is the passenger class in our case. For example, we will get <value>144</value> females who
			booked first class.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Renaming attributes with regular expressions.">
		<info>
			The names of the new columns reflect how they were created, but this is not always the easiest to read. You could use the
			operator
			<op>Rename</op>
			for manually renaming the three attributes to something nicer, like "Passenger
			Class First".
			<op>Rename</op>
			is the way to go if you only have few attributes which should be renamed,
			but we will take a more
			advanced approach which would allow you to
			rename hundreds of
			attributes at a time.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Search</activity>
				for the operator
				<op>Rename by Replacing</op>,
				<activity>add it</activity>, and
				<activity>connect it</activity>
				to
				<op>Pivot</op>.
			</task>
			<task>
				Also
				<activity>connect the operator</activity>
				to the result port on the right.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Copy</activity> <value>count\((.*)\)_(.*)</value>   
				into the <param>replace what</param> parameter field. 
				Make sure that you get all the parentheses right!
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Copy</activity>
				<value>$1 $2</value>
				into the
				<param>replace by</param> parameter.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			You might already be familiar with <emph>regular expressions</emph> (this is the name for the strange
			parameters we have used for the renaming). They are a powerful tool and can be
			found in many
			different places in RapidMiner. The expression you have used for <param>replace what</param>
			means that you look for something between <value>count(</value> and <value>)_</value> and then something else after the
			underscore. Those two elements are identified later by the round brackets.  Each time you use round brackets, you define 
			a new so-called <emph>capturing group</emph> which you can refer to in the definition of the replacement.
			Since the round brackets have a special meaning here, we need to quote the brackets in the name itself with a
			backslash. Finally, we can use the capturing groups in the <param>replace by</param>
			parameter with the dollar sign and the number identifying the group. <value>$1</value> is for
			the content of the first group, which always happens to be "Passenger Class", and <value>$2</value> is
			for identifying the second group. Those are the three different classes "First", "Second", and "Third".
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Run the process.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity><icon>16/media_play.png</icon> Run</activity> the process.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			Your data set should now have column names that look like <emph>Passenger Class First</emph>.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Congratulations!">
		<text>You rotated an aggregated data set in wide table format - good job! <op>Pivot</op> can be difficult to
			configure sometimes.
			Just keep in mind that the <param>group by attributes</param> parameter parameter will define the groups in
			the rows with one row per group while the values of the column grouping attribute parameter will define the
			new columns.
		</text>

		<questions>
			<question>
				Can you change the process so that the column names will be changed to "First Passenger Class", 
				"Second Passenger Class", and "Third Passenger Class"?
			</question>
			<question>
				Can you also change them to just say "First Class", "Second Class", and "Third Class"?
			</question>
			<question>
				Change the Pivot so that the gender is transformed into new columns and the passenger class is defining
				three groups of data. How many columns and rows are you getting now?
			</question>
			<question>
				Try to adapt the renaming so that it just uses the gender as column names after the new pivoting.
			</question>
			<question>
				Now, remove the Rename by Replacing operator and remove the column grouping attribute from Pivot. Set
				Sex and Passenger Class as group by attributes and use Passenger Class with count as the aggregation
				attribute. Run the process and inspect the result. In how far is it different from the first result you
				obtained through Pivot?
			</question>
		</questions>
		
		<info>
			Don't worry if you had trouble with challenges 2, 3, or 5. Regular expressions can be difficult at first,
			but
			they are definitely worth learning. Maybe a book can help you or you will find a lot of training resources 
			<link url="http://www.ocpsoft.org/opensource/guide-to-regular-expressions-in-java-part-1/">online</link>
			.
		</info>
	</step>
</steps>
