<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<steps>
	<step name="Learn more about advanced data handling.">
		<text>Data preprocessing is probably where you spend most of your time as an analyst.
		There are two general groups of data handling: blending and cleansing. 
		This and the next tutorial will discuss some of the most important operations for data cleansing.</text>
		
		<info>
			<emph>Blending</emph> is about transforming a data set from one state to another 
			or combining multiple data sets.
			<emph>Cleansing</emph> is about improving the data so that modeling will deliver better results.
		</info>
		
		<text>Let's look at the
		<file>Titanic</file>
		data again. You might remember from
		before that it contains some
		missing values depicted by question
		marks in the data. You can also see
		the number of missing values for
		each attribute in the
		<ui>Statistics</ui>
		view. Missing values are a problem
		for many data preprocessing or
		modeling operations. This tutorial
		will show you
		the most common approaches for removing or replacing missing values.</text>

		<info>
			This is the second set of RapidMiner tutorials. Make sure you you've completed the first set
			before clicking next!
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Prepare the data.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Drag</activity>
				the
				<file>Titanic</file>
				data into the process.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Hover your mouse pointer</activity>
				over the output port and wait for the tooltip to show the meta data.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Press F3</activity>
				while the tooltip is shown. It is now transformed into a window and
				you can scroll down to see
				the information about all the columns.
			</task>
			<task>
				Check for columns with missing values.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			There are five attributes with missing values: Age, Passenger
			Fare, Cabin, Port of
			Embarkation, and Life Boat. Cabin and Life Boat
			have the most missing values, so let's deal with them first.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Remove attributes with too many missings.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Add</activity>
				a new operator
				<op>Select Attributes</op>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Connect</activity>
				the new operator to the
				<op>Retrieve</op>
				operator and the output to the result port "res" on the right.
			</task>
			<task>
				In Parameters,
				<activity>change</activity>
				the
				<param>attribute filter type</param>
				to
				<value>Subset</value>
				and select all attributes but
				<value>Cabin</value>
				and
				<value>Life Boat</value>. This means that those
				two will be removed by the operator.
			</task>
			<task>
				<icon>16/media_play.png</icon> <activity>Run</activity>
				the process.
			</task>
			<task>
				Click on the
				<ui>Statistics</ui>
				tab and check which attributes with missing values are still left.
			</task>
		</tasks>
		<info>
			We removed
			<value>Cabin</value>
			because almost all values in this column were missing and the
			remaining values probably didn't contain a lot of useful information. We removed
			<value>Life Boat</value>
			for
			similar reasons and because this attribute is strongly correlated to the label. The attribute
			<value>Age</value>
			also has a significant number of missing values, but we will handle this using a different method next.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Replace missing values.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Search</activity>
				for the operator
				<op>Replace Missing Values</op>
				and
				<activity>add it</activity>
				to the process. You can drop it on the connection line
				between
				<op>Select Attributes</op>
				and the result port (move the mouse pointer until
				the connection is highlighted before you drop
				the new operator). This way you do not
				need to manually reconnect the operators.
			</task>
			<task>
				In the Parameters of this operator,
				<activity>use</activity>
				<value>single</value>
				for the
				<param>attribute filter type</param>
				and
				<activity>select</activity>
				<value>Age</value>
				for
				<param>attribute</param>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<icon>16/media_play.png</icon> <activity>Run</activity>
				the process again.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			Dropping operators on connection lines often saves you the manual work of creating
			the
			connections yourself. Don't worry if you did not hit the connection line with your first try -
			just re-connect the operators manually in this case.
		</info>

		<info>
			You will see in the
			<ui>Statistics</ui>
			tab that only a few examples with missing values are left. When we ran this process, the missing values for
			<value>Age</value> were replaced with the average value of <value>Age</value> - this is a common technique for 
			handling a lot of missing values for an attribute. Because there are only a few missing values left,
			we can safely filter these examples out of the data set.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Remove examples with missing values.">
		<info>
			You have used the
			<op>Filter Examples</op>
			operator already before, but this time we will use some
			advanced settings to remove examples that
			have missing values for their attributes.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Search</activity>
				for
				<op>Filter Examples</op>
				and
				<activity>drop it</activity>
				again
				on the connection line to the result port. In case you miss the connection, you can of
				course always manually connect the operator instead.
			</task>
			<task>
				Note the
				<ui>link</ui>
				at the bottom of the
				<ui>Parameters</ui>
				panel which shows/hides advanced parameters
				<activity>Click</activity>
				on
				<ui>Show advanced parameters</ui>
				to display all operator parameters.
			</task>
			<task>
				New parameters should appear.
				<activity>Set</activity>
				the
				<param>condition class</param>
				to
				<value>no_missing_attributes</value>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<icon>16/media_play.png</icon> <activity>Run</activity>
				the process again.
			</task>
		</tasks>
	</step>

	<step name="Congratulations!">
		<text>Great, you successfully handled missing values using three different approaches:
		Removing columns with missing values, replacing missing values with other values, and removing examples
		with missing values. Try solving the challenges below before you start the next tutorial:</text>

		<questions>
			<question>
				Check the
				<ui>Statistics</ui>
				tab - does it still show missing values for any of the columns?
			</question>
			<question>
				Why is it not a good idea to just filter out the examples right away instead of removing attributes
				and replacing the missings in
				<value>Age</value>?
			</question>
			<question>
				Right-click on
				<op>Select Attributes</op>
				and
				<emph>disable</emph>
				the operator. Do the same with
				<op>Replace Missing Values</op>. What do you expect if you re-run the process now? Try it!
			</question>
			<question>
				How many examples are left in the data set now?
			</question>
		</questions>
	</step>
</steps>