<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<steps>
	<step name="Repeating sub-processes.">
		<text>Looping and branching are very powerful concepts known in practically all
		programming languages. RapidMiner offers dozens of operators for looping over examples,
		attributes, or values of a specified attribute. In this tutorial, we will build a process which loops over the
		three different passenger classes of the Titanic data and checks if the number of examples is
		higher than a previously specified number. If this is the case, we sample down this subgroup to
		this number, otherwise we will just keep all examples. Processes like this can, for
		example, be used to balance classes in cases where a few very large classes dominate some minority
		cases.</text>
	</step>

	<step name="Prepare the data and a macro.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Drag</activity>
				the
				<file>Titanic</file>
				data into the process.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Add</activity>
				the operator
				<op>Set Macro</op>
				to the process and
				<activity>connect it</activity>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Use</activity>
				<value>max size</value>
				as
				<param>macro</param>
				and
				<value>400</value>
				as
				<param>value</param>
				in its
				<ui>Parameters</ui>.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			We will use
			<value>400</value>
			examples as maximum number for each of the three passenger classes later on.
			By defining this with a macro at the start of the process, it is very easy to make changes
			to
			this setting later on.
			This is especially useful if you use the value in multiple parts of the process, which we will!
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Looping over attribute values.">
		<info>
			Let's loop over the three passenger classes and check for a condition for each of the
			classes.
			In our case, the condition is that the class should have less than
			<value>max size</value>
			examples.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Search</activity>
				for the operator
				<op>Loop Values</op>
				and
				<activity>drag it</activity>
				into the process.
				<activity>Connect it</activity>.
			</task>
			<task>
				In its
				<ui>Parameters</ui>, set
				<param>attribute</param>
				to
				<value>Passenger Class</value>.
			</task>
		</tasks>
	</step>

	<step name="Inside the loop.">
		<info>
			Did you notice the shape  <icon>16/subprocess_icon.png</icon> of the 
			<op>Loop Values</op> operator? This
			shape means that this operator can have other operators nested inside of it. 
			Double-click the <op>Loop Values</op> operator to look inside of it.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Double-click</activity>
				<op>Loop Values</op>.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			Inside the loop you can define a sub-process to be executed for each
			of
			the three passenger classes we are looping over. Whenever you are in a nested sub-process,
			you can
			find the name of the sub-process in the top left corner. At the top of the Process panel you will also
			find
			a
			path which you can use to navigate back up to the main process.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Keep only examples for the current class.">
		<info>
			The concept of nested operators allows for extremely
			powerful processes. You will see this a lot in later processes when we validate models or
			optimize their parameter settings. But for now, let's just define what is happening
			inside of the
			loop.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				Make sure you are inside the <op>Loop</op> operator by <activity>double-clicking</activity> it, if you didn’t already.
			</task>
			<task>
				Inside the
				<op>Loop Values</op>
				operator, do the following:
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Add</activity>
				the operator
				<op>Filter Examples</op>.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Connect</activity>
				the input of the filter with the port on the left of the sub-process.
				This will allow the data set delivered to the Loop Operator to flow into the sub-process.
			</task>
			<task>
				In the
				<ui>Parameters</ui>
				of
				<op>Filter Examples</op>,
				<activity>add a new filter</activity>
				with the settings
				<value>Passenger Class</value>,
				<value>equals</value>, and
				<value>%{loop_value}</value> .
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			The macro
			<value>loop_value</value>
			is a pre-defined macro of the operator
			<op>Loop Values</op>
			which
			can be used inside of the operator. In each iteration, the macro is set to the current
			attribute
			value
			of the loop. You can use this macro then in other operators like, for example,
			<op>Filter Examples</op>.
			We only keep those examples of the original example set which have attribute values of the
			current
			loop
			iteration.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Branching the process based on a condition.">
		<info>
			Remember our task? We want to keep all examples of a subgroup if the number of
			passengers
			for the class is less than 400, but take a sample of the subgroup if the number of passengers is more than 400.
			To do that we need to learn about <emph>branching</emph>.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				Still inside
				<op>Loop Values</op>,
				<activity>add</activity>
				the operator
				<op>Branch</op>
				to the sub-process.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Connect</activity>
				the input of
				<op>Branch</op>
				with the output of the
				<op>Filter</op>.
			</task>
			<task>
				Also
				<activity>connect</activity>
				the first output port of
				<op>Branch</op>
				with the "out" port on the right of the
				<op>Loop Values</op>
				sub-process. This will allow us to use the results of the loop iterations in the main process.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Click</activity>
				on the
				<op>Branch</op>
				operator to get its
				<ui>Parameters</ui>.
				<activity>Set</activity>
				<param>condition type</param>
				to
				<value>max_examples</value>
				and
				<param>condition value</param>
				to
				<value>%{max size}</value> . This is the macro we have defined in the beginning.
			</task>
		</tasks>
	</step>

	<step name="Inside the Branch.">
		<info>
			Did you notice that the
			<op>Branch</op>
			operator has the same sub-process icon in the bottom right as <op>Loop Values</op> did?  In
			this case, you can actually define
			<emph>two</emph>
			sub-processes, following an "if-then-else" logic: <emph>If</emph> the condition of the
			<op>Branch</op>
			operator is fulfilled, <emph>then</emph> the first subprocess is executed, <emph>else</emph> the second
			sub-process is
			executed.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Double-click</activity>
				on
				<op>Branch</op>
				to jump inside the operator.
			</task>
		</tasks>
	</step>

	<step name="Defining the operations for both cases.">
		<info>
			You see two sub-processes named "Then" and "Else". If the size of the current subset is
			less than the specified maximum size, we just keep the complete data. Otherwise we want to sample
			it down to the maximum size.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				In the "Then" sub-process on the left, just
				<activity>connect</activity>
				the first port on the left with the first port on the right.
				That is right, we do
				<emph>not</emph>
				use any operators here.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			We just want to keep the data as is, i.e. we do not do anything with the data and just
			deliver it as result of the sub-process in this case.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				In the "Else" sub-process on the right,
				<activity>add</activity>
				a
				<op>Sample</op>
				operator and
				<activity>connect</activity>
				its in- and output ports with the ports on the left and the right
				of the sub-process.
			</task>
			<task>
				Set the
				<param>sample size</param>
				parameter to
				<value>%{max size}</value> .
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			If the example set for the passenger class in the current iteration of the loop is too
			large, we
			sample it down to the desired size and deliver the result as output of this sub-process.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Appending the three results.">
		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity>Navigate back</activity>
				to the main process at the top of the
				<ui>Process</ui>
				panel.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Add</activity>
				the operator
				<op>Append</op>
				to the process.
			</task>
			<task>
				<activity>Connect</activity>
				its input with the output of
				<op>Loop Values</op>
				and its output with the result port on the right.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			Notice the doubled line between
			<op>Loop Values</op>
			and
			<op>Append</op>. This means that the output of
			<op>Loop Values</op>
			is actually a collection of example sets instead of a single example set. The loop
			will in fact
			deliver one example set for each of the three passenger classes. This is why we added
			the
			<op>Append</op>
			operator: it combines all three sets into one single set again.
		</info>

		<tasks>
			<task>
				<activity><icon>16/media_play.png</icon> Run</activity>
				the process.
			</task>
		</tasks>

		<info>
			You should see that the total size of the data set has been reduced
			and
			none of the three passenger classes is larger than 400 cases (check out the
			<ui>Statistics</ui>
			tab).
			If this is not the case, use breakpoints to find the cause and go through this
			tutorial
			again step by
			step.
		</info>
	</step>

	<step name="Congratulations!">
		<text>Well done! This was certainly the most complex process you have built so far. It consists of
		macros,
		loops, multiple nested sub-processes, and uses collections of results. If you combine these
		concepts with the hundreds of data transformation operations in RapidMiner, you can build
		extremely powerful processes solving every data preparation problem you might encounter.
		And, all of this, without writing a single line of code!</text>

		<questions>
			<question>
				Place a breakpoint after <op>Loop Values</op> and re-run the process. Note the selector on the
				left side in the results. You can use this to switch the view of the different elements of the
				collection. Resume the process to see the appended data.
			</question>
			<question>
				Also try a breakpoint inside of the loop after <op>Filter Examples</op>. You will see the
				filtered result in each iteration when you run the process. You can resume it after 
				inspecting the intermediate results and the execution continues with the next iteration of the loop. 
				Remove all breakpoints after you no longer need them.
			</question>
			<question>
				Change the process, so that only a maximum of <value>200</value> examples for each class is used.
			</question>
			<question>
				Can you think of a process which first calculates the number of examples for all three
				classes and finds the minimum number among those?  Then, sample down each group to this number 
				so that all classes are equally frequent.
			</question>
		</questions>
	</step>
</steps>
